They should be designing for the places and the people, the landscapes that the wall endangers. Now, people are already rising to this occasion, and while the purpose of the wall is to keep people apart and away, it's actually bringing people together in some really remarkable ways, holding social events like binational yoga classes along the border, to bring people together across the divide. I call this the monument pose. (Laughter) And have you ever heard of "wall y ball"? It's a borderland version of volleyball, and it's been played since 1979 (Laughter) along the US-Mexico border to celebrate binational heritage. And it raises some interesting questions, right? Is such a game even legal? Does hitting a ball back and forth over the wall constitute illegal trade? (Laughter) The beauty of volleyball is that it transforms the wall into nothing more than a line in the sand negotiated by the minds and bodies and spirits of players on both sides. And I think it's exactly these kinds of two-sided negotiations that are needed to bring down walls that divide. Now, throwing the ball over the wall is one thing, but throwing rocks over the wall has caused damage to Border Patrol vehicles and have injured Border Patrol agents, and the response from the US side has been drastic. Border Patrol agents have fired through the wall, killing people throwing rocks on the Mexican side. And another response by Border Patrol agents is to erect baseball backstops to protect themselves and their vehicles. And these backstops became a permanent feature in the construction of new walls. And I began to wonder if, like volleyball, maybe baseball should be a permanent feature at the border, and walls could start opening up, allowing communities to come across and play, and if they hit a home run, maybe a Border Patrol agent would pick up the ball and throw it back over to the other side. A Border Patrol agent buys a raspado, a frozen treat, from a vendor just a couple feet away, food and money is exchanged through the wall, an entirely normal event made illegal by that line drawn on a map and a couple millimeters of steel. And this scene reminded me of a saying: "If you have more than you need, you should build longer tables and not higher walls." So I created this souvenir to remember the moment that we could share food and conversation across the divide. A swing allows one to enter and swing over to the other side until gravity deports them back to their own country. The border and the border wall is thought of as a sort of political theater today, so perhaps we should invite audiences to that theater, to a binational theater where people can come together with performers, musicians. Maybe the wall is nothing more than an enormous instrument, the world's largest xylophone, and we could play down this wall with weapons of mass percussion. (Laughter) When I envisioned this binational library, I wanted to imagine a space where one could share books and information and knowledge across a divide, where the wall was nothing more than a bookshelf. And perhaps the best way to illustrate the mutual relationship that we have with Mexico and the United States is by imagining a teeter-totter, where the actions on one side had a direct consequence on what happens on the other side, because you see, the border itself is both a symbolic and literal fulcrum for US-Mexico relations, and building walls between neighbors severs those relationships. You probably remember this quote, "Good fences make good neighbors." It's often thought of as the moral of Robert Frost's poem "Mending Wall." But the poem is really about questioning the need for building walls at all. It's really a poem about mending human relationships. My favorite line is the first one: "Something there is that doesn't love a wall." Because if there's one thing that's clear to me -- there are not two sides defined by a wall. This is one landscape, divided. On one side, it might look like this. A man is mowing his lawn while the wall is looming in his backyard. And on the other side, it might look like this. The wall is the fourth wall of someone's house. But the reality is that the wall is cutting through people's lives. It is cutting through our private property, our public lands, our Native American lands, our cities, a university, our neighborhoods. And I couldn't help but wonder what it would be like if the wall cut through a house. Remember those disparities between wealth and poverty? On the right is the average size of a house in El Paso, Texas, and on the left is the average size of a house in Juarez. And here, the wall cuts directly through the kitchen table. And here, the wall cuts through the bed in the bedroom. Because I wanted to communicate how the wall is not only dividing places, it's dividing people, it's dividing families. And the unfortunate politics of the wall is today, it is dividing children from their parents. You might be familiar with this well-known traffic sign. It was designed by graphic designer John Hood, a Native American war veteran working for the California Department of Transportation. And he was tasked with creating a sign to warn motorists of immigrants who were stranded alongside the highway and who might attempt to run across the road. Hood related the plight of the immigrant today to that of the Navajo during the Long Walk. And this is really a brilliant piece of design activism. And he was very careful in thinking about using a little girl with pigtails, for example, because he thought that's who motorists might empathize with the most, and he used the silhouette of the civil rights leader Cesar Chavez to create the head of the father. I wanted to build upon the brilliance of this sign to call attention to the problem of child separation at the border, and I made one very simple move. I turned the families to face each other. And in the last few weeks, I've had the opportunity to bring that sign back to the highway to tell a story, the story of the relationships that we should be mending and a reminder that we should be designing a reunited states and not a divided states. Thank you. (Applause)
Deben diseñar para los lugares, personas, paisajes que el muro pone en peligro. La gente ya se está levantando para esta ocasión, y mientras que el propósito del muro es mantener a las personas alejadas, en realidad está uniendo a las personas de maneras realmente notables, organizando eventos sociales como clases de yoga binacional a lo largo de la frontera, para unir a las personas a través de la división. Yo llamo a esto la pose del monumento. (Risas) ¿Y alguna vez han oído hablar de "wall y ball"? Es una versión fronteriza de voleibol y se juega desde 1979. (Risas) entre la frontera de EE. UU. y México para celebrar el patrimonio binacional. Y esto plantea preguntas interesantes, ¿es este juego incluso legal? ¿Golpear una pelota de un lado a otro del el muro constituye un comercio ilegal? (Risas) La belleza del voleibol es la que transforma el muro en nada más que una línea en la arena negociado por las mentes y cuerpos y espíritus de jugadores de ambos lados. Y creo que es exactamente este tipo de negociaciones bilaterales que se necesitan para derribar muros que dividen. Ahora, lanzar la pelota sobre la pared es una cosa, pero tirar piedras sobre el muro ha causado daños a los vehículos de la Patrulla Fronteriza y ha herido a agentes de la Patrulla Fronteriza, y la respuesta del lado estadounidense ha sido drástica. Agentes de la Patrulla Fronteriza han disparado a lo largo del muro,, matando gente tirando piedras en el lado mexicano. Y otra respuesta de los agentes de la Patrulla Fronteriza es erigir los apoyos de béisbol para protegerse a sí mismos y sus vehículos. Y estos respaldos se convirtieron en un rasgo permanente en la construcción de nuevos muros. Y comencé a preguntarme si, como el voleibol, tal vez el béisbol debería ser una característica permanente en la frontera, y las paredes podrían comenzar a abrirse, permitiendo que las comunidades se crucen y jueguen, y si golpean un jonrón, tal vez un agente de la Patrulla Fronteriza recoja la pelota y la devuela al otro lado. Un agente de la Patrulla Fronteriza compra un raspado, una golosina congelada, de un vendedor a un par de metros de distancia, La comida y el dinero se intercambian a través del muro. Un evento completamente normal hecho ilegal por esa línea dibujada en un mapa y un par de mm de acero. Y esta escena me recordó un dicho: "Si tiene más de lo que necesita, debe construir mesas más largas Y no muros más altos". Así que creé este recuerdo para recordar el momento que pudimos compartir comida y conversación a través de la brecha. Un columpio permite que uno entre y gire hacia el otro lado hasta que la gravedad los devuelve a su propio país. La frontera y el muro fronterizo es considerado como una especie de teatro político hoy en día, así que tal vez deberíamos invitar al público a ese teatro, a un teatro binacional donde la gente puede unirse con intérpretes, músicos. Tal vez el muro no sea más que un enorme instrumento, el xilófono más grande del mundo, y podríamos tocar este muro con armas de percusión masiva. (Risas) Cuando imaginé esta biblioteca binacional, quería imaginar un espacio donde poder compartir. libros e información y conocimiento a través de una brecha, donde la pared no era más que una estantería. Y quizás la mejor manera de ilustrar la relación mutua que tenemos con México y EE. UU. es imaginando un columpio, donde las acciones de un lado tendrían una consecuencia directa en lo que sucede en el otro lado, Porque el borde mismo es tanto un punto de apoyo simbólico como literal para las relaciones EE. UU. México, y la construcción de muros entre vecinos corta esas relaciones. Probablemente recuerden esta cita, "Las buenas cercas hacen buenos vecinos". A menudo se la considera la moraleja del poema de Robert Frost "Mending Wall". Pero el poema realmente cuestiona la necesidad de construir muros. Es un poema sobre la reparación de las relaciones humanas. Mi línea favorita es la primera: "Hay algo que no ama una pared". Porque si hay algo que me queda claro... No hay dos lados definidos por un muro. Este es un paisaje, dividido. Por un lado, podría verse así. Un hombre está cortando el césped mientras la pared se cierne en su patio trasero. Y por otro lado, podría verse así. La pared es la cuarta pared de la casa de alguien. Pero la realidad es que el muro atraviesa la vida de las personas. Se cortando a través de nuestra propiedad privada, nuestras tierras públicas, nuestras tierras nativas americanas, nuestras ciudades, una universidad, nuestros barrios. Y no pude evitar preguntarme. Cómo sería si la pared cortara una casa. ¿Recuerdan esas disparidades entre riqueza y pobreza? A la derecha está el tamaño promedio de una casa en El Paso, Texas, y a la izquierda está el tamaño promedio de una casa en Juárez. Y aquí, la pared corta directamente a través de la mesa de la cocina. Y aquí, la pared corta a través de la cama en el dormitorio. Porque quería comunicar cómo el muro no solo está dividiendo lugares, sino a la gente, está dividiendo a familias. Y la desafortunada política del muro es la de hoy, separando a los niños de sus padres. Puede que estén familiarizados con esta señal de tráfico conocida. Fue diseñada por el diseñador gráfico John Hood, un veterano de guerra nativo americano que trabajaba para el Departamento de Transporte de California. Y se le encomendó crear una señal para advertir a los automovilistas de inmigrantes que quedaron varados a lo largo de la carretera y quienes podría intentar correr a través de la carretera. Hood relató la situación de los inmigrantes hoy. A la de los navajos durante la Caminata. Y esta es realmente una brillante pieza de activismo de diseño. Y fue muy cuidadoso al pensar en usar una niña con coletas, por ejemplo, porque él pensó que es con lo que los automovilistas podrían empatizar más, y usó la silueta del líder de los derechos civiles César Chávez para crear la cabeza del padre. Quería aprovechar el brillo de este signo. llamar la atención sobre el problema de la separación de niños en la frontera, e hice un movimiento muy simple. Di vuelta a las familias para enfrentarlas entre sí. Y en las últimas semanas, he tenido la oportunidad de traer esa señal de vuelta a la carretera para contar una historia, La historia de las relaciones que deberíamos estar arreglando. y un recordatorio de que deberíamos estar diseñando estados reunidos y no estados divididos. Gracias. (Aplausos)